孙国父字幕组
字幕翻译｜荷糖月　傻兔妍　Cynthia　Olivia　Huhu
西语听译｜傻兔妍　　校对｜傻兔妍　　后期｜荷糖月
字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
一九五八年的十一月 我在读高三
November 1958,my senior year of high school.
那时其他女孩都沉醉于猫王舞步
While other girls were dancing to Elvis...
期盼着毕业舞会
and dreaming about prom dates...
而我在读简·奥斯汀 期盼着大学生活
I was reading Jane Austen and dreaming about college.
有一天我父母突然宣布
And then my parents announced...
我们要在一个星期内搬去古巴
we were moving to Cuba...in a week.
辣身舞 2
情迷哈瓦那
根据真实故事改编
不管是摔门还是以沉默来抗议
Slamming doors and giving the silent treatment...
也改变不了他们的决定
couldn't change that...
但这比承认我害怕容易得多
but it was easier than admitting I was really scared.
但至少我家人都很高兴
At least everyone else was happy.
父亲在福德公司高升了
Dad got his big promotion from Ford.
母亲可以风风光地旅行了 而苏西
Mom got to travel in style,and Susie...
她就算在飓风中也能泰然自若
I swear that girl could adjust in a hurricane.
欢迎来到海洋酒店
Welcome to the Hotel Oceana.
还不错 对吧
Not too shabby, huh?
这就是我所了解的古巴…
Here's what I know about Cuba...
我高中学的法语派不上用场
my high-school French wasn't going to help me.
一个人都不认识
I didn't know a single person...
虽然没人会谈及这个
and though no one would talk about it...
[菲德尔·卡斯特罗：古巴前领导人 推翻了巴蒂斯坦亲美独裁政权]
但菲德尔·卡斯特罗正在领导革命
Fidel Castro was leading a people in a revolution...
[巴蒂斯塔·伊·萨尔迪瓦：古巴总统 亲美独裁者]
对抗巴蒂斯塔总统
against President Batista...
至少这里你不会听到这种事
not that you would know it from this place.
这就是古巴 没人管你做什么
This is Cuba. Nobody cares what you do here.
苏西 抽烟吗
Susie, you want a smoke?
小心这小姐 她会带坏你
Watch out for this one.She's a bad influence.
我当你在夸我好了
I'll take that as a compliment.
她很快就会唆使你逃课了
She'll have you ditching classes in no time.
如果我没记错 某人
As I recall,there's a certain someone...
喜欢和我一起逃课
that likes to ditch them with me.
别忘了报名参加曼波舞课
Don't forget to sign up for mambo lessons.
每天都有课程
Mambo classes are held every day...
[琼·克莉佛：电视剧《反斗小宝贝》里一个完美主妇的母亲 完美榜样的代名词]
我的天啊 琼·克莉佛来哈瓦那了
My God. June Cleaver is in Havana.
事实上 那是我姐姐凯蒂 她很聪明
Actually, that's my sister Katey. She's a real brain.
噢 真的吗
Oh, really?
可不 她可能会考上拉德克利夫学院
Yeah. She's probably going to Radcliffe.
哦？主修时装吗
What, majoring in fashion?
过来和我们一起吧 这里有位置
Why don't you join us? There's room here.
我是詹姆斯·菲尔普斯
I'm James Phelps.
嗨 我是凯蒂·米勒
Hi. Katey Miller.
很高兴认识你
Pleasure to meet you.
- 你是不是…  - 是的
- Are you the...  - Yeah.
- 你父亲在我父亲手下工作  - 是的
- Your dad works for my dad.  - Yeah.
这是希拉 伊芙 波莉 还有史蒂夫
This is Sheila, Eve, Polly, and Steph...
你认识苏西 对吧
and I guess you know Susie,right?
你真要去拉德克利夫学院读书吗
So, are you really going to Radcliffe?
到春天才能知道
I won't know till spring.
哇 姑娘们 注意啦
Whoa. Watch out, girls.
如果你满脑袋都是课本的话
I guess if your head's in your books...
你应该没有时间
you really don't have time...
去考虑天气这种傻事了
to think about silly things like the weather.
很冷么
Chilly?
噢
Oh.
真对不起 是我的错
I'm so sorry. It's my fault.
别弄了 去给我拿一杯新的
No, just go get new drinks.
愚蠢的拉美佬
Stupid spic.
失陪了
Excuse me.
- 你要加班赔这些饮料  - 可错不在我
- Tú sabes que trabajas que pagar por eso.  - Oye que no fuera mi culpa.
工作时给我小心点
Trabajas con cuidado.
先生 打扰了
Excuse me. Senor?
有什么能为您效劳的 小姐？
How may I help you, senorita?
我撞倒了那些饮料 我想赔偿
I knocked into those drinks. I'd like to pay for them.
没这个必要 只是个意外 失陪了
That will not be necessary. Accidents happen. Excuse me.
对不起…
Yo tengo siento...
我会讲英语
I speak English...
我不需要你的施舍
and I don't need your charity.
我不是这个意思
It's not.
别担心 这没什么
Don't worry about it. It's OK.
我很抱歉 她那样叫你
I'm sorry for what she called you.
- 这没什么  - 我不这么觉得
- That was nothing.  - Not to me.
那为什么要由你来道歉？
Then why are you apologizing?
你们舞跳得真好
You guys were so good.
你妈妈很出色
Your mother was good.
我就一般般
I was OK.
- 爸爸？ - 嗯
- Dad?  - Hmm.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry
我一直对来古巴兴致不高
I haven't been excited about all of this.
宝贝 没事的
Sweetheart, it's OK.
高三把你从学校拖出来确实很糟糕
Senior year is a terrible time to drag you out of school...
况且你是班级之星啊
especially when you're the star of the class.
- 爸  - 嘿 别否认
- Dad.  - Come on. Don't deny it.
你应该感到骄傲
Be proud of it.
你在这里也会很出色的
You'll do great here, too.
我不能站在您的脚上跳舞了
I can't stand on your feet anymore.
- 嘿 你还记得这个  - 是啊
- Hey, you remembered that.  - Yeah.
非常好
Very good.
让我们继续上节课所学的内容
Let's continue where we left off.
拿出十八号课本 打开二十五页
Book 18, page 25.
凯蒂 尽力去跟上进度 行吗
Katey, just do your best to follow, all right?
没问题 这我去年就读过了
It's OK. I read it last year.
你们安静
Knock it off.
那你从第三百四十二行开始读吧
Well, then perhaps you'd like to begin reading at line 342.
此时求婚者开始载歌载舞
"Now the suitors turned to dance and song...
随着欢快的节拍摇摆
"to the lovely beaten sway...
等待着黄昏的到来
"waiting for dusk to come upon them there...
[出自《奥德赛》第18卷]
“夜幕降临 他们沉湎在欢悦之中”
and the dark night came upon them, lost in pleasure."
有没有人能告诉我们
Can anyone tell us...
这段话怎么理解？
the significance of this passage?
就是一群醉汉在胡闹咯
It's a bunch of drunk guys doing it.
雅典娜
Athena
希望求婚者们继续侵扰奥德修斯的住处
wants the suitors to keep invading Odysseus' house...
这样他就会怒杀所有求婚者
so that he'll get angry enough to kill them.
那女神为什么要这么做？
And why does the goddess want that?
她希望奥德修斯发掘自己的力量
She wants Odysseus to find his strength...
和勇气？
and courage?
非常好
Very good.
需要我载你回家吗
Need a ride home?
不用了 我可以的 我有很多功课要补
No. I'm OK. I got a lot of catching up to do.
其实 许多女孩子
You know, a lot of girls...
不会显露出她们的聪明才智
don't like to let on when they're smart.
我知道 我不该…
I know.I shouldn't have said...
不 不 我喜欢
No. No, I like that.
我喜欢那样的你
I like that about you.
星期六晚上我几个朋友要去乡村俱乐部
A bunch of us are going to our country club on Saturday night.
有乐队表演 音乐很酷
There'll be a band.The music's pretty cool.
你愿意和我一起去吗
Would you like to go with me?
我真的有很多功课要做
I really do have a lot of work to do.
在星期六的晚上？
On a Saturday night?
哇哦
Wow.
来嘛 我相信就算荷马
Come on. I'm sure even Homer took some time off...
在写伊利亚特和奥德赛之间 也有空闲的
between The lliad and The Odyssey.
那 好吧
Well, sure. OK.
好
OK.
我们都到齐了 可以开车了
We're all here now. You can go.
美女
Bonita.
就这样
Eso.
你突然受到古巴音乐的鼓动吗
You felt the sudden urge for Cuban music?
我没赶上校车
The van left without me.
已经走了一个小时了
I've been walking for an hour.
我可以送你回家
I can walk you back.
哦 不 你不必送我
Oh, no. You don't have to do that.
是的 没错
Oh, yeah, you're right.
你早晚能自己找到路的
You'll find your way sooner or later.
说不定一周或一个月就找到了
Maybe in a week or a month.
我去道个别
Let me just say good-bye.
爷爷！
Abuelito!
真棒
Bueno.
你叫他什么？
What was it you called him?
Abuelito 就是我爷爷
Abuelito. It's my grandpa.
我是凯蒂 你的名字是？
I'm Katey. What's your name?
哈维尔
Javier.
这么说 你认识五个西语单词了吗
So what, you know like five words in Spanish?
可能有十个呢
Maybe ten.
你为什么那么努力学习
And what are you studying so hard to do?
我也不知道
I haven't figured it out yet.
来 我帮你拿
Here. Let me take that.
我从没见过那样的舞蹈
I've never seen dancing like that.
什么样的舞蹈？
Like what?
我说不清
I don't know.
我很喜欢 它非常地
I like it. It's very...
- 非常古巴？ - 没错
- Very Cuban?  - Yeah.
- 我们应该离开这里  - 为什么
- We should get off the street.  - Why?
你不明白他们在唱什么
You don't understand what they're singing.
不！
No!
往那边跑！
That way!
所以你得… 没事 她回来了
So you've got... OK. Here she comes.
非常感谢您
Thank you so much.
感谢上帝 凯蒂 你去哪儿了
Thank God. Katey, where have you been?
我错过了校车
I missed the bus.
我没事 走回来的
I'm fine. I walked.
天啊 凯蒂 为什么不给我打电话
For heaven's sakes.Katey, why didn't you call me?
我担心你被叛乱分子绑架了
For all I knew, you could have been kidnapped by rebels.
你该担心的不是叛乱分子
It's not the rebels you should be worried about.
你说什么？
What did you say?
你说得对 我错了 我应该打给你的
You're right. I'm sorry. I should have called.
亲爱的 你的书包呢
Honey, where's your book bag?
我把它留在学校了
I left it at school.
太重了
It was heavy.
哦 天啊
Oh, God.
多亏这些无聊的美国书
It was good I had all these boring American books with me.
他们才认为我不是革命者
They realized I couldn't be a revolutionary.
我不明白
I don't understand.
他们只是在唱歌
They were just singing.
这里已经没有 只是唱歌 这样的事了
There is not such a thing as "just singing" here anymore.
你跳得很棒
You know,you're a pretty good dancer.
我跳得很差劲
I was terrible.
是啊 你跳得差劲
Oh, yeah. Yeah, you were terrible...
不过对一个美国人来说
but for an American
你的动作很不错了
you move well.
哦 谢谢
Oh, thanks.
你为什么要照着镜子跳呢
Why do you look in the mirror?
我在回想看过的步法
I was trying to remember the steps I saw.
可看镜子没有什么用吧
But what does looking have to do with it?
你只需感受音乐
Just feel the music.
想学舞蹈 就来看看吧
You should see for yourself.
周六晚上真正的舞者会去黑玫瑰酒吧
The real dancers are at La Rosa Negra on Saturday night.
我去不了
I can't.
有人邀请我去乡村俱乐部了
I got invited to this country club thing.
- 嘿 进展很快啊  - 是啊
- Hey, that was fast.  - Yeah.
这就是你为什么想要学古巴舞蹈吗
Is that why you want to learn Cuban dancing?
为了给你的男伴留下好印象？
Just to impress your date?
不 我想
No. I wanted to...
没事 别担心
Don't worry. Don't worry.
他们在俱乐部里可不会那样跳
They won't dance like that at the club.
学会狐步就够了
Just learn the fox trot instead.
我早就会狐步舞了
I already know the fox trot.
我们需要去逛街吗
Do we need to go shopping?
我只是在想 周六晚上你可能
I just thought you might be going to the country club...
要去乡村俱乐部
Saturday night.
你怎么知道？
Oh, you just thought?
菲尔普斯太太请我吃午饭
Mrs. Phelps took me to lunch.
你们不是在商量包办婚姻吧
You two aren't planning an arranged marriage, are you?
我怎么没想到呢
No. I should have thought of that.
詹姆斯很帅耶
He's so cute.
- 尤兰达？ - 什么事？
- Yolanda?  - Yes?
这裙子是不是很方？
Is this square?
很方？
Square?
嗯 你看…像方形吗
Yeah, you know...Iike a square?
方形好不好看呢
Is a square good or bad?
不好看
It's bad.
这样的话
Si.
那就是方形的
This is square.
噢 天啊
Oh, God.
我觉得不行吧
I don't know.
你个头比我小 你的衣服可能…
You're smaller than me.Your dresses'll be...
就它了
Perfect.
你在开玩笑吧
You're joking.
怎么了 这件也很方吗
Why? Is it square?
当然不是
Definitely not.
太不公平了！
It's not fair!
我所有的朋友都能去
All of my friends are going...
为什么你能去而我不能？
so why would you go and I can't?
我比你大
I am older than you.
真浪费 你根本不懂享乐
Such a waste. You don't even know how to have fun.
真不想我留下来陪你？
Sure you don't want me to stay?
爸 别跳了
Dad, don't.
好吧 拜拜
OK. Bye.
自己当心点
Be careful.
波丽 波丽
Polly. Polly.
天啊 她穿着什么 画上去的？
God, what'd she do? Paint it on?
小姐
Senorita.
哇
Wow!
好看吗
Oh, I don't know.
哦 很好
Oh, I do.
我诚挚邀请所有人
I would like to invite you all...
在平安夜去豪华俱乐部
to the Club Palace on Christmas Eve...
你去过豪华俱乐部吗
You been to the Palace yet?
第十届拉丁交际舞…
the tenth annual Latin ballroom...
业余舞蹈大赛
amateur dance contest.
到时我带你去
I'll have to take you.
你跳得不错 我让你紧张了吗
You feel really good.Am I making you nervous?
没有
No.
好吧 你让我有点紧张了…
Well, you make me a little nervous...
不要告诉别人
but don't tell anyone.
那可会毁了我的名誉
It'll ruin my reputation.
我们要去波丽家
Listen, we're going over to Polly's...
- 参加鸡尾酒会  - 是吗
- for a little mojito party.  - Oh, yeah?
她父母又出城了
And her parents are out of town again.
你觉得怎样？
What do you think?
史蒂夫能调出很好喝的鸡尾酒
Steph can make a wicked mojito.
嗯…
Well...
嘿 我可以让人
Hey, I'm sure we can get someone...
[原句“秀兰邓波尔”是一种无酒精饮料]
给你弄杯汽水
to rustle you up a Shirley Temple.
其实…
Actually...
詹姆斯和我要去一个古巴俱乐部
James and I are gonna go to a Cuban club.
哪儿？
Where?
黑玫瑰酒吧
La Rosa Negra.
对 我们要去…黑玫瑰酒吧
Yeah, we're going to the...La Rosa Negra.
天啊
Jesus.
你看他们享受音乐的方式
Look at the way they feel the music.
他们的确在享受
They're feeling it,all right.
我去拿些饮料
I'll get us some drinks.
嗨
Hi.
你打扮得真有古巴风
You look so Cuban.
你也是
So do you.
嗨 我是哈维尔
Hi. I'm Javier.
我叫菲尔普斯
Name's Phelps.
嗯 我听说过你
Yeah. I know you.
怎么 乡村俱乐部不尽如人意吗
So, the country club wasn't all you expected?
我们想开开眼界
We thought we'd expand our horizons a little bit.
想体验一下哈瓦那的活色生香？
Oh, you mean actually experience La Havana?
介意我和你的女伴跳支舞吗
Do you mind if I dance with your date?
这你得问她
Well, you'll have to ask her.
好呀
OK.
♫ 亲爱的哈瓦那 节奏激荡我心 ♫
♪ Te quiero Havana,the rhythm pumpin' in my heart ♪
♫ 黑玫瑰酒吧里 ♫
♪ In la rosa ♪
♫ 我们在爱的律动下起舞 ♫
♪ We dance to the tempo of love ♪
我们要不要给你男朋友表演一番？
Shall we give your boyfriend a show?
他不是我男朋友
He's not my boyfriend.
♫ 舞姿婀娜亦如言语般倾诉衷肠 ♫
♪ Let your body talk till the voice in you says ♪
♫ 宝贝 ♫
♪ Baby ♪
♫ 深渊中你找到了深情的我 ♫
♪ I'm the one you find deep in the groove ♪
♫ 潜藏着美丽的身躯和浓烈的情感 ♫
♪ That has your body and your senses ♪
♫ 韵律和爱情的碰撞让我热情似火 ♫
♪ I'm the heat inside when rhythm and love collide ♪
♫ 古巴 ♫
♪ Cuba ♪
♫ 让我来展现魅力 ♫
♪ Let me introduce myself ♪
♫ 舞吧 舞吧 ♫
♪ Represent, represent ♪
♫ 古巴 ♫
♪ Cuba ♪
♫ 舞吧 舞吧 ♫
♪ Represent, represent ♪
♫ 古巴 ♫
♪ Cuba ♪
♫ 嘿 我的音乐啊 ♫
♪ Hey, me musica ♪
♫ 舞吧 舞吧 ♫
♪ Represent, represent ♪
♫ 古巴 ♫
♪ Cuba ♪
♫ 舞吧 舞吧 ♫
♪ Represent, represent ♪
♫ 古巴 ♫
♪ Cuba ♪
♫ 嗨 你的音乐啊 ♫
♪ Hey, tu musica ♪
女伴丢了？
Lose your date?
一定是和我弟跳舞的那个美国妞
Must be that Yankee dancing with my brother.
把女友带来哈瓦那是不错
Good of you to bring your girlfriend to Havana...
趁你现在还有机会
while you still have the chance.
怎么？想赶我们走？
Why? Are you gonna run us gringos out?
没错 蠢货 你就继续笑吧
That's right, comebola,so keep smiling.
♫ 让我来展现魅力 ♫
♪ Let me introduce myself ♪
♫ 古巴 ♫
♪ Cuba ♪
♫ 舞吧 舞吧 ♫
♪ Represent, represent ♪
♫ 古巴 ♫
♪ Cuba ♪
♫ 舞吧 舞吧 ♫
♪ Represent, represent ♪
♫ 古巴 ♫
♪ Cuba ♪
♫ 嘿 你的音乐啊 ♫
♪ Hey, tu musica ♪
♫ 舞吧 舞吧 ♫
♪ Represent, represent ♪
♫ 古巴 ♫
♪ Cuba ♪
♫ 我们在哈瓦那地下起舞 ♫
♪ Orishas underground de Havana ♪
♫ 舞吧 舞吧 ♫
♪ Represent, represent ♪
♫ 古巴 ♫
♪ Cuba ♪
♫ 嘿 你的音乐啊 ♫
♪ Hey, tu musica ♪
拉乌尔和艾斯梅拉达
Raoul y Esmerelda...
是黑玫瑰酒吧的舞王和舞后
king and queen of La Rosa Negra.
当他们起舞 舞池就是他们的
When they dance,the floor is theirs.
你跳得和他一样好
You're as good a dancer as he is.
凯蒂 这是我哥卡洛斯
Katey, this is my brother Carlos.
- 这是阿图罗和米格尔  - 你好
- Arturo and Miguel.  - Hola.
你好
Hola.
我们刚才在聊政治
We were just talking politics.
是吗 我哥喜欢谈政治
Really? Well,my brother loves talking.
哈维尔可不喜欢谈政治
Javier doesn't like to talk politics.
毕竟 革命嘛
After all, the revolution...
会让他丢了给你们拍马屁的工作
would screw up his job kissing your asses.
今晚的革命在哪里？
And where's the revolution tonight?
舞池里？
On the dance floor?
你们兄弟继续亲热
While you boys kiss and make up...
我们出去透透气
we're gonna get some fresh air.
我们走吧
Let's go.
我跳得很开心
I was enjoying the dancing.
你真性感
You were very hot.
这片区可不安全
It's not the safest part of town.
不要 别这样
No, don't.
带我回家吧 可以吗
Take me home, will you...
别这样！滚开！
Stop it! Get off!
你刚才可没拒绝他
You didn't say no to him.
住手！
No!
凯蒂！凯蒂 回来！
Katey! Katey,get back in the damn car!
我载你回家
I'll take you home.
嗨
Hey.
- 他在哪？ - 他走了 已经走了
- Where is he?  - He's gone. He's gone.
没关系 没关系 我没事
It's OK. It's OK. I'm fine.
我爸在他爸手下工作
My dad works for his dad.
我只想忘掉这事
I just want to forget about it.
不用担心
Don't worry.
我送你回家
I'll take you home.
走吧
Come on.
我早该看出不对劲
I should have seen it coming.
可能是我还不习惯
I guess I'm not used to...
和流氓相处？
Bastards?
和男生啦
Guys.
怎么？你在美国没有男朋友？
What? You never had a boyfriend in America?
没有 我喜欢过一个男生
No. I liked this one guy,
但是我们不可能
but it didn't work out.
为什么？
Why not?
他根本就不认识我
He didn't know I existed.
哦 好吧 那确实是个问题
Oh, yeah.That could be a problem.
我只能送到这了
This is as far as I go.
员工不能和客人待在一起
The staff is not supposed to mix with guests.
我好不容易才找到这份工作
It took me a long time to find this job.
送我上去你就会有麻烦吗
You'd be in trouble for walking me up there?
是的
Yeah.
这规矩太可笑了
That's ridiculous.
再见
Adios.
谢谢你送我回家
Thanks for walking me home.
很抱歉你今晚过得不顺心
I'm sorry your evening was so difficult.
也不是整晚都这样
Not all of it was.
我的任务是让你光彩照人
My job is to make you look beautiful.
你的任务是让我们合二为一 看
Your job is to make our bodies like one. Watch.
谢谢 好了 今天就到这
Thanks. OK, that's it for today.
谁想参加舞蹈大赛？
Who's gonna enter the big dance contest?
不是当地人才能参加吗
Isn't it just for locals?
其实有胆量的人都可以报名
Actually, it's for anyone who has the guts to try.
你参加吗
What about you?
我？
Me?
不 我不行 我跳得不够好
No, I can't.I'm not good enough.
你行的 我看过你练舞
Sure you are. I've seen you practicing.
放松
Easy.
考虑一下
Think about it.
凯蒂！
Katey!
你的外套落在我车里了
You left your sweater in my car.
拿到学校给我就行了
Just bring it to school.
嘿 等等
Hey, wait a second.
凯蒂
Katey.
真的对不起
I'm really sorry.
我喝醉了 我从没想过要伤害你
I was drinking. I would never hurt you.
他不在这儿了
He's not here.
他被解雇了
They fired him.
什么
What?
露易丝和你妹妹看见你们在一起
Lois and your sister,they saw you.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我得走了
I gotta go.
你不能乱说话
You know, you need to keep your mouth shut.
乱说话的后果很严重
The things you do have consequences.
是露易丝说出去的
Lois is the one who blabbed it.
哦 是啊 跟你一点关系都没有
Oh, right. And you had nothing to do with it.
你干嘛和那家伙在一起啊
Well, what were you doing with that guy, anyway?
真令人难堪
It's embarrassing.
这是你想说的 还是那些女生想说的？
Is that you talking, or is it those other girls?
他跟我们不是一类人
He's not like us.
我跟你可不是一类人 苏西
There is no "us," Susie.
- 你好  - 你好
- Hola.  - Hola.
我找哈维尔
Busco a Javier Suarez.
进来吧
Si.
什么事？
Yes?
我是哈维尔的朋友
I'm a friend of Javier's.
什么朋友？
Como?
酒店里的
From the hotel.
我不知道他在酒店里还有朋友
I didn't know he had friends in the hotel.
他在家吗
Is he here?
不在 他在酒店上班
No. He's working there now.
你没看见他？
You don't see him?
她想找
Esta buscando...
没事妈妈 我认识她 待会见
Esta bien.Yo la conozco.Hasta luego.
- 到这儿来  - 快跟奶奶进去
- Ven aca.  - Gabaneas con abuela.
过来 我们进去
Venga. Vamos.
你找我弟弟什么事？
So, what do you want with my brother?
我想和他谈谈
I need to talk to him.
你让他丢了工作 还不够？
You got him fired. Isn't that enough?
我有让他赚钱的办法
I know a way he can make some money.
你们这些美国佬 跑这儿来
You Yankees, you come here...
把钱扔进赌场
and you pour money into the casinos...
塞进那帮恶棍的口袋
into the pockets of the gangsters...
他们统治着国家
who run this country,
杀害无辜的人民
the same gangsters who murder innocent people.
杀害了我父亲
Iike my father.
我不知道这些事
I didn't know.
是啊 你不知道
That's right. You don't know.
哈维
Javi.
她来这儿干什么？
¿Qué esta haciendo aquí?
抱歉你丢了工作
I feel terrible about what happened.
我去了你家
I went to your house...
我家？你跟我妈说我被炒了？
My house? You told my mother I was fired?
- 不 我没有  - 那你想干嘛
- No, I didn't  - Then what do you want?
我只想跟你谈谈
I told her I wanted to talk to you.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry you got fired.
没事 是我的错 我该注意点的
Don't worry. It's my fault. I knew better.
这是你的新工作吗
Is this your new job?
可不是 你们造汽车 我们偷
That's right.You make 'em. We steal 'em.
是吧 哈维？
Isn't that right, Javi?
我知道有个舞蹈比赛
There's this dance contest...
平安夜在豪华俱乐部举行
at the Palace...Christmas Eve.
我觉得你应该去
I think you should go.
去看看他们需不需要杂工吗
And see if they need any busboys?
我不是这个意思
That's not what I mean.
你知道什么人能进豪华俱乐部吧
You know what kind of people goes to the Palace?
我能让你进去
I could get you in.
但你要做我的舞伴
You'd have to be my partner.
你是说 跟你一起跳舞？
You mean, dance with you?
天啊 我没那么差劲吧
God, I'm not that bad.
你昨晚又不介意
You didn't seem to mind it last night.
我昨晚没想着赢比赛
I wasn't trying to win a contest.
哦 你不想吗
Oh, weren't you?
对不起 我有很多事要做
I'm sorry, but I have a lot of work to do.
半决赛的奖金是三百美元
The prize for the semifinals is $300.
最后的大奖是五千美元
The grand prize is $5,000.
获奖者还能去美国
The winners get to go to America.
我没时间
I don't have time.
[请停止杀害我们的子民！]
到这儿来一下
Cae y va un poca.
你还有小孩要照顾呢
Tiene un hermanito por aquí.
我还要去送货
Tiene que hacer la entrega
送货？随你怎么说
Entrega...Dice lo que quería.
是啊 我还得运药 你要看吗？
Sí, con cargamento de medicina. ¿Qué, te velo?
不了
No.
我很高兴你胸怀大志 卡洛斯
Me alegro de que tenga un corazón tan grande,Carlos.
希望你也能帮家里的忙
A lo mejor un día que da la ayuda por la familia.
你会明白我一直在帮忙的
Algun día trata cierto esoy ayudando
嗨
Hi.
那个舞蹈比赛
This contest...
要花钱吗
does it cost money?
不用
No.
你知道那是交际舞比赛吧
You know that it's ballroom dancing.
不是我跳的那种
It's not what I do.
是拉丁交际舞
It's Latin ballroom.
如果把你的舞和我的糅合在一起
If we mix what you do with what I do...
我们一定能擦出火花
I really think we'd have something.
那我还得从头开始教你
I still have to teach you everything.
也不是从头吧
Not everything.
我也得教你一些舞步呢
I'll have to teach you a few things, too.
我们能行吗
Can we do this?
- 怎么了  - 你在干什么
- What?  - What are you doing?
跳舞啊
Just dancing.
但这是有规则的
But this is a routine.
你不能只跟着感觉跳
You can't just do what you feel like...
想到什么就跳什么
when you feel like it.
我跳舞的时候可没有规则
When I dance, I have no routine.
但这是舞蹈比赛啊 我们需要编舞
But this is a contest. We need a structure.
我能看看吗
Can I see that?
首先 你要学会动作
First, you learn to move,
- 再去考虑要求和规则  - 好吧
- and then we worry about lists and words.  - OK. Fine.
你怎么叫这个部位？
How do you call this?
臀部？
Your hips?
扭动臀部
Move your hips.
转圈
And circle.
继续
Come on.
继续 转个圆圈
Come on. And circle.
你那是方形的
That's a box.
什么 你疯了吗
What, are you crazy?
我为什么要掩护你？
Why should I cover for you?
你要我告诉他们那天晚上的事吗
You want me to tell them what happened?
嘿 你们俩
Well, hello there.
妈！
Mom!
我们要去喝柠檬水
We're just heading over for some lemonade.
- 一起去吗  - 不 不用了
- Would you care to join us?  - No, no.
下次吧
We'll take a rain check.
好 玩得开心点
OK. You two have fun.
我会帮哈维尔 你也要帮我
I'm gonna help Javier, and you're gonna help me.
你的姿势真差
Your frame is really weak.
好点了吗
Better?
我跳舞可不会弄伤自己 谢谢
I could do without the bruises, thanks.
我们中间还能再插进一对舞伴
I can fit another couple between us.
到时舞厅不会很拥挤
It's not gonna be a crowded club.
我们要绕场一圈
We've gotta sweep across the dance floor.
行 行 跟你绕就是了
OK. OK, I can sweep.
你在干什么 你的步伐太大了
What are you doing? Your steps are too big.
不会啊 我在绕啊
No, I'm sweeping.
你和詹姆斯怎样了？
How's it going with James?
我要做功课
I got homework to do.
亲爱的 你知道吗
You know what, sweetie?
我一直想问问
I've been wanting to ask you
你和詹姆斯相处时
if you have any questions or...
有没有什么疑虑或担忧
concerns, you know, about you and James.
我好像在跟我妈的熨衣板跳舞
It's like dancing with my mother's ironing board.
闭上眼睛
Just close your eyes.
干嘛
Why?
闭上就对了
Just do it.
说出来有点奇怪
It's awkward to talk about, but...
但不能让男生强迫你 这很重要
it's important that you not let a boy pressure you.
有时你跟詹姆斯在一起
And even if you have certain feelings...
可能会有些感觉
when you're with James...
令你不太习惯
feelings that you aren't used to having...
哦 天啊
Oh, God!
男生怎么都这样？
Do you have to be such a guy?
好吧
OK.
我来做女生
OK, I'll be the girl.
你现在的决定和选择
The decisions you make now, the choices you make...
可能会影响你的一生
could affect your whole life.
你明白吗
Do you understand what I'm saying?
明白了？
You do?
我不想浪费这好音乐
I didn't want to waste the music.
嗯 当然
No, of course not.
怎么了？
What's the problem?
为什么那么害怕我碰你？
Why are you so afraid to let me lead you?
我没有
I'm not.
你有 等你能承认你害怕
You are. When you're ready to say you're afraid...
再告诉我
Iet me know.
- 嘿  - 不好意思
- Hey.  - Sorry.
不 不 别走 我快练完了
No, no, no. Stay. I'm almost done anyway.
怎么样 你决定了吗
So, what did you decide?
我决定参加比赛
I entered the contest.
这很好啊
All right. Good for you.
准备得怎样？
So, how's it going?
挺好的
Oh, great. It's going great.
真的吗
Really?
唉 其实不太好
No, it's not.
天啊 我是疯了才觉得我们能行
God, I must have been crazy to think we could do this.
两周后比赛就开始了
It's in two weeks...
每次他前进 我后退
and whenever he pushes, I pull...
我放松自己舞动起来
and I'm flowing, and I'm being free...
我转圈
and I'm making a circle...
也不再僵硬得像熨衣板
and I'm not an ironing board anymore...
可还是不行
and it's still not working.
现在他又说 你很害怕
And now he says, "You're afraid."
你害怕吗
Are you?
不怕
No.
那太糟糕了
That's too bad.
过来一下
Come here un momento.
站在这里
Stand right here.
让我看看你的姿势
Let me see your frame.
很好
Good.
手抬高一点
A little pressure.
你从哪学的舞蹈？
So, where'd you learn this?
我父母 他们都是舞者
My parents. They were dancers.
是嘛？
Really?
放松
Relax.
就这样
Yes.
把手放下
Drop your arms.
吸气
Breathe.
试试基本舞步
Now just basic.
很好
Good.
你刚刚为什么说 太糟糕了？
What did you mean when you said, "That's too bad"?
如果你不能克服心中的恐惧
If you can't move through your fear...
不能敞开心扉
and connect with yourself...
那绝对不可能
there's absolutely no way...
和舞伴心有灵犀
you're gonna connect with your partner.
听我说
Listen to me.
我知道让人触碰你的身体
I know that it's scary as hell...
会让你很害怕
to let another person touch that part of you.
但如果做得到 那就值得
But if you do, it's worth it.
现在忘掉我说的话 尽情跳舞吧
Now forget everything I just said and dance.
舞池是你的了
The floor is yours.
回见
I'll see you.
好吧 我承认
OK, I am.
承认什么？
You're what?
我害怕
Afraid.
动作要像水一样灵动
So the movement has to be fluid like the water.
非洲古巴舞 是奴隶的舞蹈
Afro-Cuban dance, it's the dance of slaves.
只有跳舞的时候 他们才能感到自由
When they danced, it was their only time to feel free.
所以他们可以像鸟儿一样
So they could be a bird, you know...
或者跳弗拉明戈舞步
or do a flamenco step
嘲笑他们的主人
and make fun of their owners.
又或者融入大海
Or just be in the sea...
忘记自己被困在远离家园的岛屿上
instead of being stuck on an island away from home.
翩然起舞时
It's a dance
你会成为理想的自己
about being exactly who you want to be in that moment.
你的动作一定要像
It has to feel and look
海浪般自然
as natural as the waves.
潮来
Coming...
潮往
and going.
潮来
Coming...
那时我们在吃晚餐 有人来敲门
We were having dinner, and there was a knock on the door.
两名警察把我父亲带走了
Suddenly two policemen were taking my father away.
谁都可能出卖了我父亲
The traitor could have been anyone.
到处都是巴蒂斯塔的特务
Batista has his spies everywhere.
你知道吗 这就是命
That's the thing, you know?
我父亲没有伤害过任何人
My father never hurt anybody.
他只是一个自由思想者
He was just a free thinker...
但有人不喜欢他的想法
but someone didn't like his thoughts.
我们举行了葬礼 但是没有找到尸体
We had a funeral but we never found his body.
卡洛斯害怕他会成为下一个受害者
Carlos disappeared for a while,
到外面躲了一阵
afraid he would be next...
一天有个女孩抱着孩子来我家
and then this girl shows up with a baby...
说是卡洛斯的 她养不了
says it's his and she cannot afford it...
突然间我肩负起了养活全家的重担
and suddenly I'm in charge of my whole family.
可能这不是你想要的生活
Maybe it's not what you want for yourself...
但是你却做得很好
but you are making a difference.
人们正在进行革命 而我在做什么
There's a revolution out there, and what am I doing?
只是给赃车涂新漆 回家带孩子
Just painting stolen cars and baby-sitting.
不 你维持了全家的生计
No, you're keeping your family alive.
这就是最重要的事
That's the most important thing you could do.
如果我们真的赢得比赛
If we could really win this contest...
说不定我能带家人搬到美国去
maybe I could bring my family to America with us.
你的父母 真是优秀的舞者
Your parents, they're perfect.
他们多么渴望将对方拥入怀中
You see how much they want to be in each other's arms?
我们一起跳舞 我是说真正的舞蹈
For us to dance together, I mean really dance...
就应该是这样
that's how it has to be.
哦 你们继续
Oh, don't let us interrupt you.
不 我们只是…
No, we were just...
嗯 我们看见了
Yeah, we saw.
听着 哈维尔 如果你想点干正事
Listen, we have more stuff in the alley...
巷子里面还有东西要搬
if you want to do something useful, Javier.
我该回家了
I should get home.
想起来回家了？
Thanks for stopping by.
离宵禁还有半个小时呢
It's half an hour before curfew.
你去哪了 参加马戏团了？
What'd you do, join the circus?
你想说你跟詹姆斯出去了？
You're gonna tell me you were out with James?
你是这么跟你妈说的
That's what you told your mother.
我可没把苏西的话告诉她
I never told her what Susie said.
苏西乱说的
Susie was wrong.
好吧
OK.
晚安 爸爸
Good night, Dad.
嗨
Hi.
你要多久才能消气？
How long you gonna be mad at me?
这里的女孩真是
The girls here.
我跟露易丝说我喜欢 简·爱
I told Lois that I like "Jane Eyre"...
她居然问我简·爱演了哪部电影
and she asked me what movie she was in.
对不起 我告了密
I'm really sorry that I told on you.
哈维尔不是那样的人 我错了
And what I said about Javier, I was wrong.
苏西 你要为自己想想
You gotta think for yourself, Suze.
我知道
I know.
我想你了
I miss you.
我好想跟你聊聊最近的事
Well, I've been dying to tell you.
这次你能保密吗
Can you keep a secret this time?
糟糕
Coño.
你要去哪？
¿Adónde tú vas?
今晚可是平安夜 别说你要去工作
Es Nochebuena. XXX dice que vas a ir a trabajar.
我要借你的西装穿
Necesito tu traje.
为什么？
¿Y eso?
我要去参加舞蹈比赛
Voy a una competencia de baile.
在哪儿？
¿Dónde?
豪华俱乐部
En el Palace
你想借西装去巴蒂斯塔最喜欢的地方？
¿Y tú quieres ponerte el traje para ir al lugar favorito de Batista?
不 我要去赢得除夕夜的五千美元大奖
No, lo quiero para ganarme 5000 canas que dan de premio en año nuevo.
当然了 你要去拍那些美国佬的马屁
Sí, claro, meneándole el culo a los americanos.
还有古巴佬的呢
Y a los cubanos, también.
苏西 我和你妈妈有个坏消息要告诉你
Susie, your mother and I have some very disappointing news.
我知道你有多想装饰圣诞树…
Now, I know how you love to decorate the Christmas tree...
唱圣诞歌和看家庭影片…
and sing carols and watch home movies...
但是恐怕今晚…
but I'm afraid tonight...
我们都要去豪华俱乐部
we're all gonna have to go to the Palace.
- 我们都去？ - 是的 苏西 全家人
- All of us?  - Yes, Susie, all of us.
我知道今晚是你和詹姆斯的约会之夜
I know it's your big night with James...
不过 能给老爸留支舞吗
but you think you could save your old man one dance?
什么时候决定的？
When did this happen?
你知道你爸这人的
Well, you know your father.
到处说我们会跳舞
Blabs to everyone we were dancers.
所以菲尔普斯家邀请我们去看
So the Phelpses invited us to
拉丁交际舞大赛
the Latin ballroom contest.
我听说那里的舞跳得很好
Where I hear the dancing is supposed to be pretty good...
但我和你妈妈会去那里挑刺儿
but your mother and I will be looking out for mistakes.
我真想看你父母惊讶的表情
I can't wait to see the looks on your parents' faces.
别刺激我
Don't remind me.
我是不是该责备你
I really should be scolding you...
总是带她出去
for keeping her out till all hours.
不用担心 夫人 我们没有做出格的事
Don't worry, ma'am. We've done nothing you'd disapprove of.
我敢保证
I can promise you that.
谢谢
Thank you.
这边请
Here.
你们两个真般配
You two make a very cute couple.
现在很多美国女孩到这儿来
So many of the girls coming over from the states these days...
都变得 有点儿野了
get a little, you know, wild.
有这样可爱的女儿真是你们的福气
You're lucky to have such lovely daughters.
女士们先生们 圣诞快乐！
Ladies and gentlemen, Merry Christmas!
一会儿
In just a few moments...
今晚的特别节目即将开始
we'll begin this evening's special event.
我们什么时候才能一睹冠军的风采？
So, when do we get to see the championship dancers?
我们可算不上是冠军
We're hardly champions.
你们真谦虚
You're just being modest.
快跳吧
Come on.
我从没看过你们在公共场合跳舞呢
I've never seen you guys dance in public before.
我想如果你丈夫不介意的话…
Actually, I thought if your husband didn't mind...
你和我可以…
you and I might...
詹姆斯…
James...
凯蒂可能想跳舞哦
Maybe Katey would like to dance.
你想跳舞吗？
Would you like to dance?
我想去洗手间
I have to find the ladies' room.
我陪你去吧
I'll escort you.
不用 我自己可以
No, no, I'm fine.
- 你去哪儿了？ - 对不起 我刚…
- Where have you been?  - I'm sorry. I was...
这主意太疯狂了
This was a crazy idea.
不 我们会赢的
No. We're gonna win.
万众期待的时刻到来了
This is the moment you have all been waiting for...
拉丁交际舞大赛正式开始！
the Latin ballroom competition!
前三名的舞者将晋级
Three talented couples will be chosen...
除夕夜的决赛
to compete in the finals on New Year's Eve.
- 太美了！ - 谢谢
- ¡Qué bonita!  - Gracias.
女士们先生们
Senoritas and senores...
欢迎哈瓦那夜晚最璀璨的明星
presenting the brightest star of the Havana night
萝拉 马丁内兹！
Lola Martinez!
凯蒂呢
Where's Katey?
等等吧
Just wait.
哦 我的天啊！
Oh, my God!
♫ 奇妙的是当我凝视你的双眸 ♫
♪ Funny thing is when I look into your eyes ♪
♫ 察觉外表掩饰下的你竟如此真诚 ♫
♪ I sense something so sincere in your disguise ♪
♫ 耳边私语 我疑是梦中倾听 ♫
♪ You whisper secrets I hear only in my dreams ♪
♫ 醒来之后却若置身五里雾 ♫
♪ Then I wake up to your tele-smoke screen ♪
♫ 你暧昧不清而我耐心静候 ♫
♪ I wait patiently while you play your game ♪
♫ 因为终究 ♫
♪ 'Cause in the end ♪
♫ 我依然是最大赢家 ♫
♪ I'll be the winner all the same ♪
♫ 当曲终人散时你将一目了然 ♫
♪ You'll see clearly when the song comes to a stop ♪
♫ 我会是率先献吻的人 ♫
♪ I'll be the one blowing kisses from the top ♪
♫ 所以 宝贝 别抵抗了 你被包围了 ♫
♪ So, baby, stop, you're surrounded ♪
♫ 我的爱团团围住了你 ♫
♪ I got my love, love all around ya ♪
♫ 走错一步 你便会淹溺在我的爱涛中 ♫
♪ One wrong move, and I'll drown ya ♪
♫ 一切都将结束 不如向我投降 ♫
♪ And that'll end ya, you should surrender ♪
♫ 只有投降 你才会成为赢家 ♫
♪ You'll never win unless you give in ♪
♫ 所以 宝贝 别抵抗了 你被包围了 ♫
♪ So, stop, baby, stop, you're surrounded ♪
♫ 我的爱团团围住了你 ♫
♪ I got my love, love all around ya ♪
♫ 走错一步 便会淹溺在我的爱涛中 ♫
♪ One wrong move, and I'll drown ya ♪
♫ 一切都将结束 不如向我投降 ♫
♪ And that'll end ya, you should surrender ♪
♫ 只有投降 你才会成为赢家 ♫
♪ You'll never win unless you give in ♪
♫ 何不给我们的爱一次机会？♫
♪ So won't you give our love a chance? ♪
♫ 难道你只是逢场作戏？♫
♪ Or do you only wanna dance? ♪
♫ 你的双唇贴近我的脸庞 ♫
♪ You put your lips very closely to my face ♪
♫ 却又逃逸无踪 展开了爱的追逐 ♫
♪ And then you run away, and so begins the chase ♪
♫ 我是猎手 而你祈祷也没用 ♫
♪ I'll be the hunter, but, boy, you better pray ♪
♫ 只要我想要 你逃不出手心 ♫
♪ 'Cause when I want ya, I'll get you anyway ♪
♫ 你深知我的作风 这已不足为奇 ♫
♪ You know what I wanna do, it ain't nothing new ♪
♫ 我厌倦暧昧不清 当我走向你时 ♫
♪ I'm tired of dropping clues, so when I step to you ♪
♫ 你是要配合我呢？♫
♪ Will you rise to my occasion ♪
♫ 或者要逼我改变立场？♫
♪ Or will you make me change your station? ♪
♫ 别抵抗了 你被包围了 ♫
♪ Stop, you're surrounded ♪
♫ 我的爱团团围住了你 ♫
♪ I got my love, love all around ya ♪
♫ 走错一步 便会淹溺在我的爱涛中 ♫
♪ One wrong move, and I'll drown ya ♪
♫ 一切都将结束 不如向我投降 ♫
♪ And that'll end ya, you should surrender ♪
♫ 只有投降 你才会成为赢家 ♫
♪ You'll never win unless you give in ♪
♫ 所以别抵抗了 你被包围了 ♫
♪ So, stop, stop, you're surrounded ♪
♫ 我的爱团团围住了你 ♫
♪ I got my love, love all around ya ♪
♫ 走错一步 便会淹溺在我的爱涛中 ♫
♪ One wrong move, and I'll drown ya ♪
♫ 一切都将结束 不如向我投降 ♫
♪ And that'll end ya, you should surrender ♪
♫ 只有投降 你才会成为赢家 ♫
♪ You'll never win unless you give in ♪
♫ 何不给我们的爱一次机会？♫
♪ So won't you give our love a chance? ♪
♫ 只要你牵着我的手 ♫
♪ If you take my hands ♪
♫ 由我带舞 我会令你翩然起舞 ♫
♪ And follow my lead, I'll make you dance ♪
♫ 我会让你翩然起舞 ♫
♪ I can make you dance ♪
♫ 但倘若你自乱阵脚 ♫
♪ But if you get my feet and miss the beat ♪
♫ 我便无法冒这个险 ♫
♪ Then I can't take that chance ♪
♪ I can't take that chance ♪
♫ 只要你牵着我的手 由我带舞 ♫
♪ If you take my hands and follow my lead ♪
♫ 我将令你翩然起舞 ♫
♪ I'll make you dance, I can make you dance ♪
♫ 但倘若你自乱阵脚 ♫
♪ But if you get my feet and miss the beat ♪
♫ 我便无法冒这个险 ♫
♪ Then I can't take that chance ♪
♫ 我便无法冒险 ♫
♪ I can't take it ♪
♫ 所以别抵抗了 你被包围了 ♫
♪ So, stop, stop, you're surrounded ♪
♫ 我的爱团团围住了你 ♫
♪ I got my love, love all around ya ♪
♫ 走错一步 便会淹溺在我的爱涛中 ♫
♪ One wrong move, and I'll drown ya ♪
♫ 所以别抵抗了 你被包围了 ♫
♪ So, stop, stop, you're surrounded ♪
♫ 我的爱团团围住了你 ♫
♪ I got my love, love all around ya ♪
♫ 走错一步 便会淹溺在我的爱涛中 ♫
♪ One wrong move, and I'll drown ya ♪
♫ 一切都将结束 不如向我投降 ♫
♪ And that'll end ya, you should surrender ♪
♫ 只有投降 你才会成为赢家 ♫
♪ You'll never win unless you give in ♪
♫ 何不给我们的爱一次机会？♫
♪ So won't you give our love a chance? ♪
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
评委已经选出了晋级三对舞者
the judges have chosen our three finalist couples for next week.
他们是 五号
And they are couple number five
荷赛·维拉尔德和爱丽丝·梅萨！
Jose Velarde and lris Mesa!
九号
Couple number nine
帝诺和洛德丝·马特尔！
Tino and Lourdes Martel!
还有…
And...
二号
couple number two
哈维尔·苏亚雷斯和凯蒂·米勒！
Javier Suarez and Katey Miller!
我们到底做错了什么
What could we have possibly done...
你要这样伤害我们？
to make you want to hurt us so much?
在众人面前羞辱我们
You humiliate us in front of everyone...
你爸爸的上司也在
including your father's boss.
你知道他可能会丢了工作吗
What, did you figure that he'd lose his job...
- 没人会丢工作  - 你会丢了工作？
- No one's losing their job.  - You going to lose your job?
不会的 去睡觉吧
No. Please, go to bed.
我什么都没做
I didn't do anything.
- 你撒谎了  - 我知道 对不起
- You lied to us.  - I know, and I'm sorry...
但我知道你不会让我去试试的
but I knew you wouldn't let me try...
当众亲吻一个古巴穷小子？
Kiss a Cuban pool boy in front of everyone?
我们当然不会让你这么做
You're damn straight we wouldn't.
而且你为什么要伤害詹姆斯？
And why in the world would you want to hurt James?
我以为你喜欢他
I thought you liked him.
不 是你喜欢他
No, you liked him...
因为完全他符合你上流社会的要求
cause he fits into your perfect country club world.
那又没什么错
There's nothing wrong with that world.
是没有 但他的手很不老实
No, but he couldn't keep his hands off me.
什么 发生什么事了？
What? What happened?
没什么 我没事
Nothing happened. I'm fine.
你为什么不告诉我们？
Why didn't you tell us?
因为我不想搞砸你的工作
Because I didn't want to mess up your job!
凯蒂 你怎么会这么想
Katey, how could you think...
我的工作能比你重要吗
that my job would be more important than you?
我没有想过要伤害你们
I didn't want to hurt you.
我只想帮哈维尔 这是他名字
I just wanted to help Javier,which is his name, by the way.
上帝啊 我真喜欢跟他跳舞
Oh, God, I love dancing with him.
哦 凯蒂
Oh, Katey.
你没想过他可能在利用你吗
Did it ever occur to you that boy might be using you?
一个单纯的美国女孩
A nice American girl
就能带他逃离哈瓦那？
who can be his ticket out of Havana?
不是这样的
That's not true.
你或许喜欢和他跳舞
You may love dancing with that boy...
但你有更重要的事情要考虑
but there are more important factors here...
比如你的家庭和未来
Iike your family and your future!
为什么只能二选一？
Why does it have to be either-or?
就因为你放弃了你热爱的舞蹈
Just because you gave up your passion,
我就也得放弃吗
why should l?
凯蒂
Katey.
凯蒂 等下 宝贝 等一下
Katey, wait. Honey, wait!
我要去找哈维尔
I'm going to Javier's.
你妈只是想保护你
Your mother's just trying to protect you.
无论你和妈妈怎么想
I'm gonna be out there on New Year's Eve...
我除夕要在他家过了
no matter what you and Mom think.
别再撒谎了
No more lies.
他在外面庆祝呢
He's out celebrating...
所以如果你要等他
so if you want to wait for him...
凯蒂打电话来了
That was Katey.
没事了 她跟哈维尔的妈妈一起
It's OK. She's with his mother.
是我错了吗
Was I wrong?
你没错
No...
不过凯蒂也没错
but neither was Katey.
有时我真希望我们…
Sometimes I wish we...
如果我们没有…
I just try to imagine what it would be like...
现在的一切会是怎样呢
if we hadn't had...
我这么想是不是个坏母亲？
Does it make me a bad mother?
当然不是
Of course not.
你当时舞跳得真好 怀念一下也无妨
You were good.It's OK to miss it.
他们一定会打破我们平静的生活 不是吗
They sure spiced up our old routine, didn't they?
我也觉得
I'll say.
即使在罗斯兰德也未必比现在好 对吧
That wouldn't have gone over too well at Roseland, would it?
对
No.
伯特 她已经不是一个小女孩了
Bert, she's not a little girl anymore.
你在看什么呢
What are you reading?
[何塞·马蒂：古巴卓越的诗人，杰出的民族英雄和伟大的思想家]
何塞·马蒂的书
Jose Marti.
这是我爸的
It was my father's.
为安全起见 我们丢掉了他所有的书
We got rid of all his books just to be safe, but...
但我留下了这本
I kept this one.
嘿
Hello.
- 哈维尔？ - 怎么了？
- Javier?  - Yeah?
如果我们没能赢得决赛
lf we don't win the finals...
我们会赢的
We will.
但如果没有…
But if we don't...
我半年后不去上大学了
I'm not gonna go to college in six months.
不知道半年后你会怎么想呢
You don't know how you're gonna feel in six months.
我知道
Yes, I do.
你不知道
No, you don't.
我不想你为了我放弃梦想
I don't want you to give up your dreams for me.
但我有了新的梦想
But I have new dreams now.
苏西 我们去泳池边吃自助餐吧
Susie, why don't you and I go raid that buffet by the pool?
好
Sure.
这棵树真漂亮
Tree looks nice.
你爸爸和我讨论过了…
Your father and l discussed it...
我们认为你应该
and we think that you should do...
决赛时做一组两圈平转动作
a double turn at the finals.
你喜欢我跳的舞？
You like the way I danced?
凯蒂
Katey...
如果让我同意你俩在一起 我做不到
if you're asking me to approve of you and this boy, I can't.
但你们的舞蹈…
But the dancing...
真是太精彩了
The dancing was incredible.
我觉得我也有点功劳
I think I should take a little credit for that.
我也觉得
I think you should, too.
- 嗨  - 嗨
- Hi!  - Hi!
哈维尔 这是我爸妈
Javier, these are my parents.
哈维尔 很高兴认识你
Hi, Javier.It's nice to meet you.
很高兴认识你们
Nice to meet you, too.
我很荣幸能见到这么优秀的舞者
It's an honor to meet such wonderful dancers.
这是从我妈花园里摘的
This is from my mother's garden.
谢谢 你真贴心
Thank you.That was sweet of you.
- 这是给你的  - 谢谢
- This is for you.  - Thanks.
- 我们走吧？ - 好
- Shall we?  - Yeah.
今晚我们将欣赏拉丁交际舞初赛中
Tonight we bring you the three winning couples
晋级的三对舞者
from the Latin ballroom competition.
想跳支舞吗？
Do you want to dance?
你敢
Don't you dare!
新年快乐 女士们先生们
Feliz año nuevo, ladies and gentlemen.
欢迎来到拉丁交际舞业余组决赛现场
Welcome to our Latin ballroom amateur dance contest final.
今晚你们轮流上台表演
You will dance on the stage one couple at a time.
冠军将获得五千美元奖金
Tonight's winning couple will win $5,000.
你们第一个出场
You are up first.
第一组选手是荷赛·维拉尔德先生
Our first couple this evening is Mr. Jose Velarde...
和爱丽丝·梅萨小姐
and Miss lris Mesa!
不要忘了看评委
Don't forget to look at the judges.
其他的就别担心了
Don't worry about the others.
记住 你是黑玫瑰酒吧的舞后
Remember, you're the queen of La Rosa Negra.
今晚表演的最后一组选手是
Our final contestants this evening...
凯蒂·米勒小姐和哈维尔·苏亚雷斯先生
Miss Katey Miller and Mr. Javier Suarez.
抱歉
Sorry!
他拿着枪！
He's got a gun!
不
No!
快走 我会去找你的！
Go! I'll find you!
你承认所有罪行吗？
¿Qué le suela todo?
革命万岁！
¡Viva la revolución!
快跑
Ahora.
- 你疯了吗  - 干嘛？
- ¿Tú ¿estás loco, o qué?  - ¿Qué?
那么多人在场
Toda la gente que estaban ahí…
要是你没有捣乱 我就可以完成任务了
Todo habría salido bien si tú no la hubieras cagado,chico.
对 什么任务 杀人吗？
¿Bien? ¿Bien, que cosa, matar gente?
你要像他们那样做坏事？
¿Cómo lo hacen ellos?
我跟他们不一样
No es lo mismo,
这些人杀了我们的父亲
esa gente que está allí mató a nuestro padre.
你这样做也会杀了别人的父亲
Pero le pudiste haber matado al padre tu también.
你真让我失望
Diego, estaría desilusionado contigo
不
No.
是我对你们两个很失望
estaría desilusionado con los dos
见鬼去吧
¡vete para el carajo!
真奇怪…
Como lo extraño…
有时我真想进父亲的房间去…
A veces pienso que en cualquier momento va a entrar por la puerta
找他的书
Buscando sus libros.
你今晚所做的一切
Lo que hiciste esta noche,
还有你为我们家所做的一切
y todo lo que has hecho por nuestra familia...
谢谢你 弟弟
Gracias, mi hermano.
听着
oye
你是个很糟糕的舞者
Eres tremendo bailarín…
你还是个很糟糕的服务员呢
Y tu tremendo camarero.
革命万岁！
¡Viva la revolucion!
各位贵宾请注意
Attention, all hotel guests.
巴蒂斯塔总统已潜逃出境
President Batista has fled the country.
这里暂时没有危险 请联系前台
There is no immediate danger.Please contact the front desk...
不敢相信真的发生了
I can't believe it's real.
你不想出去和他们一起庆祝吗？
Don't you wanna be out there celebrating?
不 我只想跟你在一起
No. I wanna be right here with you.
我们没有赢得比赛
We didn't win the contest.
对
No.
但鼓励奖也挺不错的
But the consolation prize was pretty good.
我真开心能和你见证这一切
I'm so happy I can see all this with you.
怎么了？
What?
没什么
Nothing.
告诉我
Tell me.
卡洛斯
Carlos...
他总说等革命来了
he always said that when the revolution came...
卡斯特罗会把所有美国公司撵走
Castro will kick out all the Yankee companies.
但你还不确定啊
But you don't really know that.
是啊 但我是说…
No. I'm just saying that...
什么 我可能会被迫离开？
What, that I might have to leave?
有可能
It could happen.
但他们不能那么做
But they wouldn't do that...
革命的思想不就是给人民自由嘛
not if the whole idea is to give people their freedom.
是古巴人民
Cuban people.
好吧 那你就和我们一起走
Well, then, you'll come with us.
我相信我爸可以帮我们
I'm sure my dad can work it out.
那我家人呢？
And my family?
我们会派人去接他们
We'll send for them,
就像我们之前想的那样
just like we were always gonna do.
凯蒂 我想离开是因为巴蒂斯塔的统治
Katey, I wanted to leave because of Batista,
但现在…
but now...
但你又不知道这里会怎样
But you don't know what life will be like here.
我是说 如果情况没有好转呢？
I mean, what if it doesn't get better?
我父亲为古巴革命牺牲了
My father died for this.
我得相信它会好起来
I have to believe it will.
我留在这能有所作为
I can make a difference here.
这是你教给我的
You showed me that.
这是我的祖国 我的家
This is my country.It's my home.
哦 感谢上帝
Oh, thank God.
凯蒂 你还好吗？
Katey, are you OK?
我们要离开了
We're leaving.
是的 你爸爸正在安排这事儿
Yeah. Your father's making arrangements.
把梳子给我
Give me that comb.
你小时候 当我要帮你梳打结的头发时
When you were little, you used to hide under the bed...
你会躲到床底下
when I'd try to comb out these knots.
凯蒂 我一生就爱过你爸一个人
Katey, your father's been the only man in my life...
所以我不知道跟爱人告别是什么感觉
so I don't know what it's like to say good-bye to someone.
但是跟我的另一个挚爱…舞蹈 告别时
Saying good-bye to dancing, the other love of my life...
我的心都碎了
it broke my heart.
后来你出生了 接着是苏西
Then you were born,and then Susie...
我太爱你们俩了 我…
and I loved you both so much that l...
你想说一切都会好起来的
You're saying I'll get over it.
不 我不是这个意思
No, I'm not. No.
我是说我知道你很痛苦
No. I'm saying I know you're hurting.
一切都糟透了
Everything's such a mess.
你可以选择
You have a choice.
什么都不做
You can do nothing.
就躲在床下…
You can hide under the bed...
或是梳开这些结
Or you can work through the knots.
我会想你的
I'm gonna miss you.
我也会想你的
I'm gonna miss you, too.
我会念着你离去
I am taking you with me.
我会把你藏在心中
I am keeping you here.
哈维尔曾说过 跳舞
Javier once said that dancing...
就是在那一刻成为理想的自己
is about being exactly who you wanna be in that moment.
和他跳舞时 我意识到我成为了
Dancing with him,I realized I was becoming...
最想做的自己
exactly the woman I wanted to be.
我们没有赢得比赛
We didn't win the contest...
但我们赢到了更重要的奖励
but we did win something more important to us.
在哈瓦那的最后一晚
On my last night in Havana...
我们是黑玫瑰酒吧的舞王和舞后
we were king and queen of La Rosa Negra.
我们不知道何时能再见面
We didn't know when we would see each other again...
但我知道这不是我们的最后一支舞
but we knew that this wasn't our last dance.